<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Narative of Edmond Nangle of Cloandarah, 1665]</title>
            <author>Nangle, Edmond.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50619</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828145</idno>
  <idno type="VID">32572</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248501655</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M172</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216414</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828145</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99828145e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50619)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32572)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1856:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[Narative of Edmond Nangle of Cloandarah, 1665]</title>
                  <author>Nangle, Edmond.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Dublin? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect?.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: Edmond Nangle.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Ireland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Catholic converts --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Saints --  Ireland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Miracles --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Apparitions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:32572:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:32572:1"/>
            <head>In nomine Patris, &amp; Filij, &amp; Spiritus Sancti, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ith most humble submission to the most glorius, blessed, and holy Trinity, the most purely immaculate and most blessed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> mother of our most glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and mercifull and most omnipotent King and Redeemer Jesus Christ, and the most true and earnest Intercessour for us poor wretched and contemptible sinners, and the true Queen of Heaven and Earth; And with my most humble, fervent, and christian Prayers begging the continuance of her most splendant and ever effectuall Intercession for the detecting of the radiant light and splendour of the true Catholick faith throughout this vail of tears from the mists of ignorance, heresy, commission and omission, and that she in her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding mercy may graciously be pleased to let me for ever be enrolled and continued in the most Royall list of her Souldiers, as one of the unworthyest of them, praying also in all humility that the glorious Angells and Apostles, my most blessed Patron and effectuall Intercessour S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
               <hi>Patrick,</hi> Bishop and Patriark of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and others the Saints and Celestiall company of that most mighty Court, may in cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency and pity of me a wretched sinner, make intercession for my being received into that most glorious and Heavenly Kingdom when it shall please the King of Kings and the Redeemer of us all, to cause the Trumpet to sound that most welcom Call for my being transferred from this miserable,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:32572:2"/>wicked, contemptible, and loathsome world, where black Satan is so nimble, that he must not onely tearm, but really and in effect prove himself a good Souldier in deed, whose Castle he shall not batter; I, a loving brother of you true Christians, and a well wisher to such as erre, do here in the presence of the most Royall, Glorius and Angelicall Court, present to your view and consideration a true and perfect Narrtive of the condition which my wickedness and sinful course of life brought me into, and also of the most mercifull and most miraculous deliverance I had out of that endless grief and sad state whereinto I almost had eternally elapsed.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Know then (I pray you,) that at the time of holding a generall Assizes in the Town of <hi>Mullingarre,</hi> for the County of <hi>Westmeath,</hi> being in the latter end of the month of <hi>February</hi> last past, the King of Kings seeing that I was unworthy the incomparable protection of his <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lorius co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, admitred certain instruments to devise and prepare for me a poisoned cup, which I then took not at all, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or suspecting the designe of those instruments (for whose good I heartily do pray as I humbly conceive my self bound to do for that it being most true, the evil which they intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to me, proved afterwards the introduction to my great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est happiness: Note that the said Assizes was in the week after the Sunday, which was upon the 19 of the said month, and before the Sunday which was upon the 26. of the same month, upon which day (I continuing in my errour with a strong resolution) went to pray with the Protestants then in the Town both before and afternoon, and upon the Monday then next after which was the 27. day of the said month of <hi>February</hi> finding my self very much weakened by the operation of the poyson, did take horse and ride to a place called <hi>Bonbrosny</hi> about four miles distant from <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingarre,</hi> and in the road to <hi>Ballinack bridge,</hi> and resolving to lodge that night at <hi>Bonbrosny,</hi> could not sleep all the night being so much tormented by the burning operation of the poyson: And the next morning which was Tuesday
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:32572:2"/>the last of the said month of <hi>February,</hi> in observance of my duty to Sir <hi>William Aston</hi> Knight, the then Judge of Assizes, I rode back to <hi>Mullingarre,</hi> from whence I gave my attendance upon him to the Town of <hi>Longford,</hi> finding my self very much spent and weakened as I travaileed, and after the Judge had sat in the Sessiions house of <hi>Longford</hi> and had made a Speech unto the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of that County (who then were assembled there in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to his precept) I humbly craved his favourable liberty to retire my self to the poor place of my abode called <hi>Cloankir</hi> about 3 miles from <hi>Longford,</hi> where I remained for that night, and being Tenant to this place where I now am; upon Wednesday morning which was the 1. day of <hi>March</hi> now last past, although I found my self very much weaker, yet remembring that the Judge promised upon the Saturday following which was the 4. of <hi>March</hi> to take a Boat which I was to provide for him and the Lord <hi>Aungier</hi> at a place upon the River <hi>Camlin,</hi> called <hi>Ballikeny,</hi> and two miles distant from <hi>Longford,</hi> and to visit my habitation, here I did (notwithstanding my indisposition) ride hither, where on Wednesday night I could not sleep, and about midnight with an intent as well to see the Lady <hi>Lane</hi> who then was at <hi>Rahcline</hi> on the side of <hi>Loghrea</hi> and a small Mile Southward from <hi>Ballileag,</hi> as well to impart to her what happened to me, and to consult her what might be best for me to do therein, as also to provide in the said Town of <hi>Ballileag</hi> a large Boat for the Judges and the Lord <hi>Aungiers</hi> purpose hither; I determined to go to <hi>Rahcline,</hi> where I was not long arrived, on Thursday morning which was the 2. of <hi>March</hi> last, before I was admitted to speak with the Lady <hi>Lane,</hi> to whom having imparted that I purposed, she desired me to go along with her by the water of <hi>Loghrea</hi> to a house of the Lord <hi>Dillon's</hi> called <hi>Kilnefaghny</hi> in <hi>Dillons</hi> country about a mile from the side of <hi>Loghrea,</hi> and being got so far as beyond the Island <hi>Eniscloghrin,</hi> were by a high wind driven to land at <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phide</hi> in the <hi>Calloe</hi> about 3. miles by land from <hi>Rahcline,</hi> and in the evening of that same day arrived at <hi>Rahcline,</hi> where I stayed not above an hour when after making known to the Lady <hi>Lane</hi> how extraordinary weak I sound my self, took my leave of her,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32572:3"/>and that night did arrive here being about 6. miles by water from <hi>Ballileage,</hi> and after a little sta<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ing sleep I suddainly <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> finding in my sel<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an extraordinary pain, and <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t on my <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and taking a horse a Friday morning did ride <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>road for an hour or thereabouts, and meeting with <hi>Bartholomew N<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>gle</hi> my <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and with severall of my friends, who hearing of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition I was in, came to see me, and delivering some of the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son that came out at my fundament to my Father in a l<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ttl<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> p<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ce of paper, I entred the house with them, and so bega<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to dictate to my brother in law M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>James Moore</hi> my will, which <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in no order finish, having lost my speech and men cry, and <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o being uncloathed was laid on a bed without hope or poss<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>li<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>v of recovery by means of any art or Physick that man could devise being now quite spent by the force of the venom, and so conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued that <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>iday night which was the 3. of <hi>March</hi> last in a most miserable condition.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The next day which was Saturday the fourth of <hi>March</hi> aforesaid, came to me one <hi>John Carr</hi> now called Dean of <hi>Ar<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> at whose presence, I (as being then a Protestant) was very joy full, who after he had spent some time telling <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e that <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in my necessity call on him he would be forthcoming; he depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from me who that Saturday night was in a more wretched condition then before.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Now know I pray you, that the Sunday following, it came in my mind to tell my Wife that I desired to converse with a rationall man that was a Priest, and thereupon desired to speak with Father <hi>Patrick Keeran</hi> a Priest, who being sent for, came to me, and he having put me some questions, it pleased Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God that I declared my self a Roman Catholick, and so prayed Father <hi>Keerans</hi> prayers for my Soul as also that he would please to do such office to me as to a dying man was sit to minister. And Loe Now my dear brethren and friends, and you our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, whose strayed condition I with tears do lament, come and listen to what I shall tell you, and you will all (I doubt not) believe that the Almighty and most mercifull King th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> me the sword of eternall vengeance if I shall not here decla<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:32572:3"/>whole naked and plain truth, to my best power, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and memory, and nothing but the truth, and what I saw, heard, and sensually know to be truth; Lo then, when Satan saw how likely it was that he should loose one, whom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was cock sure, upon the cieling over my head he shews me a blew beam of about some 7. or. 8. foot long, the edge of it as sharp as a Sythe, and backwards from it went whirling blew <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ams, and in t<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e middle of it was a half circle as if therein he would have threatned to place my neck, and to chop ost my head, and so it held over my h<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d in that manner; at length as I lay in my bed sometimes the edge of it went forwards, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ling smoaks brought it again backwards, and <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> placed severall devices of <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wheels, and brass <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>yling <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ces, whereby i<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was continued in such admirable t<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>tures, and t<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ments that it is not possible for me to find tearms sufficient to express them; and being thus most wretchedly and <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ly tormented, on Monday night which was the 6. of <hi>March</hi> last, it assuredly came in my mind that M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Carre</hi> was the man in whose hands my relief wholly consisted, and that at the first call he would be with me, and withall, a very great fear possessed me that I had offended Mr. <hi>Carre</hi> by what I had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to Mr <hi>Keeran,</hi> but for Sir. <hi>Carre</hi> I earnestly called, who (poor man) although he was not personally in the house with me that Monday at night, as all my people and friends who were there then do averre, and as he himself (I hope) will confess, he representatively suddainly appeared to me, and was not long with me when he possessed me that he himself was the person in whose hands I solely was, and that <hi>Keeran</hi> had no power there, and what he made me believe was but to delude me: And when he had thus wonne me again, he promises to go under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath to the Furnaces and wheels, and command them for to cease, when he was gone, another thought possesses my mind, that perhaps it were but reasonable to bring Mr. <hi>Carre,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Keeran</hi> both together before me, and to see them both dispute the validity of their commissions, that so I may see which had the best card to shew, whereupon I called Mr. <hi>Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:32572:4"/>and by my cogitations (as I supposed) he understood from me what had before passed between Mr. <hi>Carre</hi> and my self, and how Mr. <hi>Carre</hi> was gone for to command the wheels and furnaces that were cleaving me up along the middle of my back-bone, and boyling me in the brass for to cease; And that if he found himself capable of making out that his commission from God Almighty for the salving of my Soul was better then Mr. <hi>Carres,</hi> I would be glad to see it discussed before me: And Mr. <hi>Keeran</hi> having asked me if I resolved absolutely to surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to him the whole power of the house, and to stick to him. he doubted not but he could quickly decide the controversy, and overcome Mr. <hi>Carre,</hi> and cause him to lay down his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission before my face; Thus my consent and firm promise be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing past to Mr. <hi>Keeran,</hi> he immediately sets strong guards a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Castle, so as Mr. <hi>Carre,</hi> and such as were his servants therein could not depart: Whilst Mr. <hi>Keeran</hi> had been thus setting the watch and guards about and over the Castle, Mr, <hi>Carre</hi> enters in a very great rage, (the so<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> wheeles were now at work nimbler then ever before) and all the men and women that were in the room with me he marked by clip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping part of every ones garment or hair, in token of the interest he pretended to them, and coming at last to my beds side, fell a clipping of severall things about me with his two handed sis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sers like unto a Cotners, threatned to let me sink through the bed, and quite into the force of the wheels &amp; middle of the boiling furnaces; In this great agony and perplexity, I begun to cry out and lament horribly, and call earnestly to God Almighty for mercy justice, and judgment: And above that blew beam upon a splendant, lightsome, and glorious stage that chaced quite away the blew one, my ever most renowned Patron and effectuall Intercessour blessed St <hi>Patrick,</hi> Patriark and Apostle of <hi>Ireland</hi> did appear, with his staff in his left hand, and hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up his right hand, assuring me that if I did throughly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve to believe as one of his flock, he would intercede for me, and in signall testimony of my willingness so to do, <hi>I</hi> held up my right hand and heart, offering up my Soul as an engagement
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:32572:4"/>for my true loyaly to the most mighty, most mercifull, and most glorius, and most royall King of Kings, as a true and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect servant of the ever renowned and blessed Champion S. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick,</hi> my ever honoured Parron, who suddainly facing towards the Heavens failed not to intercede for me, and being through my back divided in two parts up to my very heart, <hi>I</hi> called a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud to my Intercessour S. <hi>Patrick</hi> speedily to procure my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief in being delivered from the hands of the spirits of darkness, and cryed out against the Devil and all his plots and works, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely renouncing and defying him and them; And upon that Royall stage appeared unto me the right hand of a woman (as <hi>I</hi> at the first s<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght imagined,) holding forth a small pair of sissers fastned to the thumb with a small goulden chain, and presently shewed forth her head and part of her shoulders, all over vailed, and <hi>I</hi> then was made to understand that it was the most glorius, most mercifull, and most blessed Queen of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, the most immaculate Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> mother of our most dear, most blessed, and most mercifull Lord Jesus Christ, the onely Saviour and Redeemer of us all unthankfull, unworthy, miserable forgetful, and wretched sinners, of whom <hi>I</hi> had an encouragement that she will now clip away all the t<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>yes and snares that Satan &amp; his instruments had intangled me in, and set me at free liberty; Being now encouraged to call my good friend Father <hi>Keeran,</hi> who by this time had handsomely and orderly set the watch, which by his prayers he did from the Heavens procure to be over and about the Castle; Mr. <hi>Carr</hi> all this while lay lurking near my bed, just ready to snap off my head, and sink my body down among the terribly wheels, and into the boyling furnaces upon the least advantage of my cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations which were numberless and very changing, occasioned by the strong and close siege which the nimble and powerfull enemy the Devil had layen to me; Now enters the truly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioned Capt. Father <hi>Patrick Keeran,</hi> who seeing so many of his Kings subjects for small pretentions layed flat on the ground by the procurement of Satan, having set his mark on them for faults not yet examined before the great King of Kings
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32572:5"/>and in his mercifuli power, yet consisting either to be <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> scoared upon, or forgiven them, as he graciously shalbe pleased to do, He couragiously revives the spirits of the miserable, daunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and wretched sinners, and stoutly approaches me, whom when <hi>I</hi> perceived to be so magnanimious, <hi>I</hi> prayed that he would please to prepare the Alter for celebrating of Mass, and having set the Alter in due order, he then approaches Mr. <hi>Car,</hi> whom he asked for his commission to be there disturbing the poor christians, Mr <hi>Carre</hi> answered him, that he had a right to every one that was there: And thereupon good Father <hi>Keeran</hi> tould him he must withdraw thence, which words were no sooner spoken, then the vices and screws of all the wheels and furnaces were opened, and Mr. <hi>Carre,</hi> with a numberless band were tumbled down that way, and so the shuts of those wheels and furnaces fastened on them.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. Now my dear Brethren, and my other loving acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and friends, whose condition <hi>I</hi> from my heart do la ent, see the true effects of my noble Patron and Intercessours promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, For lo! Southward of the place where the truly good man Father <hi>Patrick Keeran,</hi> upon Tuesday morning which was the 7. of <hi>March</hi> last, begun the most blessed office of celebrating Mass, there is a narrow window which was then stopped with some things to keep the light from my eyes, that being (as the poor lamenting people who were about me fittest for one in my condition as they in all likelihood and possibility judged me to be a man irrecoverable as to bodily health,) but mat this win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow <hi>I</hi> observed a little of the morning light to enter, in my thought about the breadth of a shilling, and at that place en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred the most radiant, splendant, and glorious beam that ever eye could see, and as the holy Mass was a clebrating, the beam did not extend straight forward a cross the room, but bent it self above the good Priests head, and on the wall over the Alter, the most glorious, most powerfull, and most blessed splendour of the divine Trinity continued untill the holy Mass was ended; Let men t forget to tell you that the blessed Sacrament of the body of Christ when lifted up in the hands of the good Priest
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:32572:5"/>Father <hi>Keeran</hi> was coloured red, At the same time there were two other Masses celebrated, but the most happy, most blessed, and most glorious splendors that appeared at the first holy Mass celebrated by Father <hi>Patrick Keeran</hi> appeared not at either of the other holy celebrations.</p>
            <p n="5">V. Upon Tuesday night which was the 7. of <hi>March</hi> aforesaid, one <hi>Garret Nangle</hi> my near kinsman and a Priest, (seeing that it pleased Almighty God to inspire in my heart to declare my self a true Catholick, and well knowing my wickedness and sinfull manner of life in the time <hi>I</hi> had spent in errour,) out of his meer and humble zeal to God Almighty, in order to the perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the duty of his function, and out of his fervent love to me, and not knowing how <hi>I</hi> was tormented, and how encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to bear the utmost of them torments, considering that it were necessary <hi>I</hi> should be tyed, threatened, and made to tepent me more largely of my sins, did with the assistance of some others, (good men,) and of my own friends and relations tie my hands and legs fast to the bed, and my body also, which occasioned that the Devil then was very nimble with me, persuading me that <hi>I</hi> had done my self the greatest injury imaginable to put my self into the hands of such people, as (besides the hazard of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall torment) used me before <hi>I</hi> was yet dead or put into my Coffin in that cruell manner, and the tyes being so painful to me, helped on the temptations of Satan to take place, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now again fully perswaded that in Mr. <hi>Carre</hi>'s power was all the relief <hi>I</hi> could expect, <hi>I</hi> called upon him aloud, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to rail wickedly against the Priest and the rest, and to cry out against my friends; Whereupon Mr. <hi>Carre</hi> appears to me, assuring me that if now <hi>I</hi> shall stick close to him and repeat me of what <hi>I</hi> had done, he would take care for to blow up into the air all that were about me and save my self; which motion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing well with my inordinate passion <hi>I</hi> embraced, still co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitating that it was good and necessary to call aloud upon the name of God almighty, imagining that through my intercessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the glory of God would now again appear to me in Mr. <hi>Carre</hi>'s aid, whom <hi>I</hi> could not judge (now) to be other then
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:32572:6"/>a true servant of Gods, being apparently used and handled by the other persons after that cruel manner: And Mr. <hi>Carre</hi> now plants a number of great Guns under me where the wheels and sp<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> before had been, and gave order that the Guns should <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ring untill those tormenters that were about me, (as <hi>I</hi> judged them who were really my good and loving friends a<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> acquaintance) should be blown up into the air, and I continued safe, and being thus kept for a great while in a most grievous torment, <hi>I</hi> begin now to cry out with great and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessant voices unto the Heavens for rel<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ef: And it then was made known unto me that my head, hands, and legs should be parted from my body, and the body it self blown into the air; which occasioned that <hi>I</hi> now again begin to con ider that Mr. <hi>Carre</hi>'s endeavours were to delude me, with which considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>I</hi> was given to understand from below, that all the Guns were a charging, and that with one vally of shot after that my head and limbs were chopped off my body, which now was filled full of base vermin, should be blown up into the air; Whereupon <hi>I</hi> begin to cry out against all that were about me in generall, judging them as well as Mr. <hi>Carre</hi> to be all Devils, which occasioned my couzen <hi>Garret Nangle</hi> and the rest (as well they might) to judge that <hi>I</hi> was now possessed with De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils that made me talk so, and making the tyes now again much faster on my hands, legs, and body, my couzen <hi>Nangle</hi> now and then gave me some whips on the face and breast when <hi>I</hi> begun to talk of Devils, or offer to break loose, requiring me to hold my tongue, which in truth made me now to judge that he and the rest of my friends did intend to murder me, for my right hand being so fast tyed to the one side of the bed, and my left hand to the other side by strugling with my body <hi>I</hi> pulled both my arms two inches at least out of my shoulder joints; And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now again settled in my resolution of crying out unto the King of Kings, and unto the Heaven for relief and justice against all generally that did occasion my confusion, or any waves di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert my thoughts from the heavenly throne; I am now loosed, and looking round on every one that was about me, and shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32572:6"/>them how my armes were, which I no ways could lift up but by lifting my body, and how all my body was, and my face with those stripes: I begun to ask them if it was not ill done of them to use their friend so, and naming every one by their names, wished that God might please to forgive them; And seeing now the great Guns were not suffered to fire, and by recollecting my memory, apprehending that in all my agony my fervent and devout prayers to Heaven was the sele mean where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I obtained any relief, I begun heartily to pray, by rehearsing the Lords Prayer, Ave Maria, and the Creed, and having set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in my self a devout resolution, there comes severall bright lightenings from the Heavens, that chaced away all the diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall spirits that were about me, which lay numberless in my bed cloaths that were over me, and within the cushions that the people laid under my head and shoulders; And seeing this incomparable chivalry, which so radiantly was acted without the noise of Guns, it made my heart rejoyce, for now the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernall spirits are blacked and burned, and in numberless legions driven down to hell, and now instead of the noyse of great Guns, <hi>I</hi> hear the most pleasant end sweetest harmony that ever ear could hear, like unto a very great number of Fryers singing of Psalms, descending from the Heavens; And now <hi>I</hi> am en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged from Heaven, and assured that I am by the mighty hand of God brought through the very blackness of the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of Hell, the gates whereof being now again shut up close, and made fast upon the spirits of darkness; And see my friends, if the words <hi>salus infirmorum, refugium peccatorum,</hi> and <hi>consula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix affl<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctorum,</hi> be not now properly attributed to the most blessed, and most immaculate Virgin <hi>Mary:</hi> For loe, through her Intercession there descends from Heaven a great number of blessed bees, which entred my belly and all my bowels, dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving out as well the vermin that were in me, as also sucking and carrying away from my body all the scum and flth of them, and of the force and effects of the venom, most pleasantly and sweetly doing the work they were commanded to do, without the least anoyance to my belly or any of my guts.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:32572:7"/> VI. And my dear Brethren and friends, having now related to you as briefly os <hi>I</hi> could the effects of Tuesday night, I hope you will give me leave to tell you, that I am of opinion, the Priest <hi>Garret Nangle</hi> and others have done carefully, devoutly, and honestly in all their actings to me, although I confess the usage of that Tuesday night occasioned, that I again was deluded by Satan, in judging them to be my open enemies, and himself my very ready and nimble friend; But you, (<hi>I</hi> hope) will agree with me in this, That it were but unreasonable in any of us to expect our King of <hi>England</hi> ought to undergo the trouble of coming in person to every one of us his humble Subjects here, that shall be running or seduced to commit any illegall act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Laws of the Realm, to divert us from such our evil intentions, other then by the laws to us al eady prescribed, and by the daily proclaiming of them to us by his Deputy, Judges, and other Ministers: If the truth of the thing it self, nor this instance, may suffice to convince any incredulous person, to whose sight this may chance to come, let him make retrospecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into that passage of <hi>Lazarus;</hi> And this being confessed, we may all conclude, that it may be by so much the more unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable in us sinners, to expect that the King of Kings ought, and is as it were bound to demonstrate to every one of us seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally how splendant his heavenly power is, other then by the direct and infallible letter of his Law, considering that we know that he has set a day for the finall hearing and judging of all his subjects that have been, and shall be in this little Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house, since the commencement of its being, until that great day, And therefore it being undeniable that my couzen <hi>Garret Nangle</hi> &amp;c. as to his Priesthood and christianity is effectually good, yet in so much as he is made of the same mettle with us all, we may believe him to be subject to sin, and the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Satan as we our selves are prone to be whilst we are in the same habit with our play-fellows, it being very evident that the Devil shews the nimblest tricks and readyest pranks up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the stage, and is never off it, untill (for shame) the villain sees but any glimps of the eternall glory, and then, Oh how like
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32572:7"/>himself he looks, We may then well say, that all is not gould that glisters, for all his nimbleness, he creeps into the darkest hole he can find, and when the light approaches him, all his pride that shined in the dark, is now but absolute dirt, and he himself like a cashiered cheating officer, tumbled headlong down from whence he came: Oh that you could but see how he looked, and yet the traitor was not overcome by the force of Cannon shot, but by the light of glory: and the noyse that he and his Cannons made when tumbled down from whence they came, being like unto great rocks tumbled down into bottomless pits, was extraordinary pleasing to me, not doubting but the villains powder is made so dank, and his guns so far sunk, besides the shamefull cracks and repulses his other screws, wheels and furnaces had received, That (my dear bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and friends,) when <hi>I</hi> am shedding of tears, fearing least the traitour catch any of you in his clutches: I again do cheer up my self, hoping that whilst the villains instruments are in so great disorder, and will take a great deal of time to six them after so shameful a rout as he met withall, We may all now shake hands, and by the great glory of God keep the dirty cheating Goaler in his own stinking prison untill he be quite smothered, for if he had not made this Play-house his with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing room, he had long since been smothered, and that is suffered him through our freedom, because (forsooth) we are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to shut out our doors against any pretty fellow that shall come to the play. Upon Wednesday morning, when the truly good Priest Father <hi>Patrick Keeran</hi> was celebrating the office of the holy Mass, there did appear a Coffin a pretty distance from the Alter, which indeed I at the first sight did take to be a coffin prepared for my self, until observing it to stand with the head upward without any support, I begun to look more earnestly on it: And lo, when the elevation was begun, the half of the board that fac'd towards the Alter was opened, and out of it the most blessed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> mother of our most mercifull Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, shewed her head and shoulders overvailed, stretching forth her hand, holding her beads on her
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:32572:8"/>fingers, and knocking her breast with far more fervency of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion then any that was in the room, and as she drew her head and hand too so the coffin closed, and as often as she stretched forth her hand the coffin opened, and when the Mass was end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it did not farther appear.</p>
            <p>Now then know I pray you, that for filling up the breaches which the fiery wheels, furnaces, and vermin made in my body, there was laid under the smal of my back a great quantity of bees wax about the bigness of a Smiths Anvile, whereof was as much melted into my body and all my limbs as made me f rmer and sounder then ever before I was, and my arms were left at the same length, and made up stronger then ever before they were, and are now two full inches longer then before they were; Note farther, that there was a goulden chain drawn through my very eyes, and every other part of my head and body by a splendant white thing, that so often as it came forth appeared unto me as broad as an ordinary plate without doing me the least hurt: and that a pin was screwed down through my skull and brain, and knocked by St. <hi>Patrick</hi> my most blessed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned patron, who gave it three knocks, whereupon the skin and flesh of my head that was before loose like unto a piece of a cow hide put on a dead mans skull, begun to fasten, and my hair that was rotting and falling apace, fasined also; For which, as I am the most wicked of all wretches, and the most contemptible of all sinners, so its most certain that I am unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of offering once to turn my face towards that glorious Throne, and in no wayes able to render due thanks unto my most merciful and most glorious King and Saviour for the least of his mercyes extended to me, who never believed directly in his Law, never feared his Justice, never refrained my self from wickedness, but gave the bridle to vice, and all obedience unto my own appetites; And as I am now the most ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and forgetfull of creatures, and a most contemptible sinner, if not remembring, every day to do evil and to offend my most mercifull Lord and Saviour, most certainly forgetting daily to do good, and therefore unworthy and most impudent to open
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:32572:8"/>my lips in so much as once the naming of him, and much more the begging of any the least of his gracious favours of indem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pn ty: But Oh, I do know there is mercy in abundance with my King, and I therefore will again most humbly and fervently beg the most effectuall intercession of the most immaculate and eternally blessed Virgin, mother of our Saviour Jesus, and of all the Archangells, Angells, Apostles, of my most renowned and effectuall Intercessour S. <hi>Patrick,</hi> and of all the rest of that most Celestiall Court, for the true instructing of my self, my Parents, Wife, Children, Family, Kindred, Relations and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, for the lightening of such as are blinde, for the bringing home of such as are strayed, and particularly for this poor Island, and for my being received as the unworthy est of that heavenly company into their society at the last day through our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, Amen. And so I conclude.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From</hi> Cloandarah <date>
                     <hi>the first of</hi> April <hi>in the year of our Lord God,</hi> 1665.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>A true well wisher of all the world.<lb/>
                  <hi>Edmond Nangle.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>